Guide to New Neighbors: Sunset Park's Chinese Community oral histories 1994.007
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Chan, Kwok-Wai, 1993 April 17; 1994.007.06
  Chan, Kwok-Wai; Mak, Paul; Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Chinese language; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; English as a second language; Flatbush Avenue (New York, N.Y.); Hong Kong (China); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Chen, Yan, 1993 April 23; 1994.007.07
  Yan Chen was born in 1974 in Mainland China. Her family moved to the United States in 1983 when Chen was about nine years old. They lived in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn, in a building their grandfather owned, as well as the Chinatown neighborhood of Manhattan. Chen went to elementary school in Chinatown for three years and then the family moved back to Sunset Park. Her parents worked in Chinatown. Chen attended Robert F. Wagner Middle School and Murry Bergtraum High School in Manhattan. When she was a teenager, her father got a job at Bay Ridge Restaurant, in Sunset Park, and her mother worked in a factory in Brooklyn. Chen also worked for a brief time sewing clothes in a factory. At the time of the 1993 interview, Chen was a young adult exploring her world of work and life.
  In this interview, Yan Chen talks about her life in Mainland China where she was born and grew up; the family home, farm, her family, extended family, and many farm animals. Chen recalls how, at age ten, she and her family came to the United States through the help of extended family. She remembers that her parents were hoping to make a lot of money in America without having to work too hard. The interview mainly consists of Chen discussing her relationship to the two areas where she lived—the Chinatown neighborhood of Manhattan and the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn—and her sense of place within them. She describes her family experiences, her education and friendships, demographic shifts within the neighborhoods, problems with bullying, crime and gangs, Chinese home ownership, and the establishment of Chinese businesses; all factors which helped to stabilize the Chinese community and allowed her family to prosper. Interview conducted by Mary Lui.
  Chen, Yan; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese American families |z New York (State) |z New York; Chinese Americans |x Employment; Ethnic relations; Illegal aliens |z United States; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.) |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Chin, Huan Reng, 1993 April 16 and 28; 1994.007.08
  Huan Reng "Benson" Chin was born in 1922 to a merchant-class Chinese family in Bangkok, Thailand. When the Sino-Japanese war broke out, Chin—aged fourteen—became a spy for the Japanese Resistance Committee of Overseas Chinese. Chin experienced World War II, the Cultural Revolution, and the Chinese Communist Party as a spy and revolutionary. In 1984, aged sixty-two, Chin immigrated to New York City; where he took work as a dishwasher in Manhattan's Chinatown. He later moved to Brooklyn's Chinatown in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. At the time of the 1993 interview, Chin looked forward to retirement.
  In this interview, Huan Reng "Benson" Chin discusses his involvement in the Sino-Japanese war; conducting espionage for the Chinese Communist Party. He recalls his military education in Marxism/Leninism and fighting in World War II. Chin speaks of the Chinese Cultural Revolution; including detention in labor camps, mass starvation, and numerous civilian suicides. Chin evaluates life after his 1984 immigration to New York City; Chinatowns of the boroughs, Sunset Park street crime, and looking forward to retirement. Interview in Cantonese conducted by Mary Lui.
  Chin, Huan Reng; Zhongguo gong chan dang.; Bangkok (Thailand); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); China |x History |x Cultural Revolution, 1966-1976; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community information services |z New York (State) |z New York; Crime |z New York (State) |z New York; Hong Kong (China); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z New York; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Pearl Harbor (Hawaii), Attack on, 1941; Sino-Japanese War, 1937-1945; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; World War, 1939-1945
- Chow, Wong Lai, 1993 December 1; 1994.007.09
  Wong Lai Chow was born in 1920 in Guangzhou of mainland China. Although her parents moved to America when Chow was a very young girl, Chow remained in China. As an adult, she married, had three children, joined the National People's Party (KMT) and received a degree in education from Zhong Shan University. During the Chinese Cultural Revolution, Chow's mother attempted to rescue her from China; for this, Chow suffered years of public humiliation and three years of hard labor. After her mother successfully sponsored her visa application in 1980, Chow brought her family to America. At the time of the 1993 interview, Chow was an active retiree in a senior hospital apartment in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn.
  In this interview, Wong Lai Chow describes her life's history; which spans the Japanese invasion of China, World War II, the Korean War, the Chinese Cultural Revolution, and her immigration to America in 1980. She recalls her career as an educator during the Chinese Cultural Revolution, being charged with "illicit relations with a foreign country," and re-education at a hard labor camp. Chow also speaks from her perspective of an active retiree in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. She discusses neighborhood crime, the Chinese mafia, and unlicensed dentists of Sunset Park. Chow also observes the challenges faced by her children, who came to America without command of English or many marketable skills. Interview conducted in Cantonese by Ka-Kam Chui.
  Chow, Wong Lai; Mak, Paul; Zhongguo guo min dang.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); China |x History |x Cultural Revolution, 1966-1976; China |x Politics and government |y 1949-1976; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z New York; Guangzhou (China); Hong Kong (China); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Labor camps |z China; Old age homes |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Quacks and quackery |z United States; Refugees; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Chow, Yui Man, 1993 April 16; 1994.007.10
  Yui Man "Michael" Chow immigrated to New York City with his family in March of 1991 at age twelve. Chow is the youngest of three children. At the time of the 1993 interview, Chow had been in Brooklyn for just two years. Still, his experiences had made him confident of his future in New York City, and he did not wish to return to China.
  In this interview, Michael Chow describes his journey to America, taken when he was age twelve. He discusses his experiences of adversity; homesickness, missing family members, learning English, assimilating to American culture and the American education system, traveling and sightseeing, playing ball games, and receiving an American name. As he makes friends, Chow says he enjoys America, and favors it over China. Interview in Cantonese conducted by Mary Lui.
  Access is available onsite at Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library. Use of oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires permission from BHS by contacting library@brooklynhistory.org.
  Chow, Yui Man; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Cultural assimilation; Education |z New York (State); English as a second language; Factories |z New York (State) |z New York; Guangdong Sheng (China); High school students |z New York (State) |z New York; Hong Kong (China); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Queens County (N.Y.); Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Flodsand, June, 1994 May 9; 1994.007.11
  June Flodsand was born circa 1942 in New York City to Norwegian immigrant parents. Raised in a working-class family, she lived on 58th Street in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn beginning in 1958. She is the eldest of six children. Flodsand's life has been spent in an equal ratio of hard work, innocent socializing at neighborhood soda shops and ice cream parlors, and activities at the Lutheran Church. After graduating high school Flodsand married. She has spent her life as an observant Lutheran and proud Norwegian American. Remaining a Sunset Park resident, she called 59th Street home at the time of the 1994 interview.
  In this interview, June Flodsand recounts her life as a working-class, first-generation American, a devout Lutheran of Norwegian parentage. She remembers an innocent childhood of family chores, a first job as a soda jerk, and weekly participation in church and its activities. As an adult, Flodsand married a fellow Lutheran and continued a life devoted to work, church, Norwegian-themed festivities, and socializing. Flodsand laments the Brooklyn neighborhood of Sunset Park's transition from a dominant Scandinavian culture to a largely Chinese and Hasidic population. She was interviewed at the Lutheran Church where she is a member. Interview conducted by Gregory Ruf.
  59th Street Lutheran Brethren Church.; Flodsand, June; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Clubs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic relations; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Lutheran Church |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Norwegians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Scandinavian Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Working class |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Giordano, Tony, 1993 June 29; 1994.007.12
  Born in 1948, Tony Giordano spent his pre-adolescent years in the Carroll Gardens neighborhood of Brooklyn. He grew up surrounded by a family of Italian heritage with three siblings as well as Italian American and Irish American friends and neighbors. In 1961, the family moved to Sunset Park, Brooklyn, a neighborhood with a strong Puerto Rican heritage and an influx of Irish and Italian Americans. Giordano attended Brooklyn Technical High School and Staten Island Community College. After a brief foray into engineering work with the New York City Transit Authority, he became a teacher. His civic-minded upbringing led to a role as a neighborhood leader in Sunset Park.
  By outlining the experiences of the two prior generations, Tony Giordano explains in the interview how his family of Italian heritage came to be in Brooklyn. He focuses in on his father’s occupations; ultimately one as a bus driver. Giordano describes his upbringing in terms of his family’s apartment housing, Brooklyn neighborhoods, vacations on Long Island, education from first grade through college, and his Roman Catholic religious experience. The interview is in depth on his experience of losing faith in organized religion and later discovering a devotion to God. Contributing to this struggle with religion, Giordano talks about a failed first marriage, custody challenges over his son, a rekindled relationship, and a happy, interfaith marriage and family. He focuses on the ethnic heritage and late twentieth century makeup of the Sunset Park community and his role as a civic leader. The influx of large numbers of Chinese into Sunset Park in the late 1980s has created what Giordano calls the “Third Chinatown.” Interview conducted by Gregory Ruf.
  Giordano, Tony; Apartment houses |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Civic leaders |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Interracial marriage; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Religious education of children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Hoen, Yee, 1993 August 17; 1994.007.13
  Yee "Curie" Hoen immigrated to New York City from Hong Kong as a young adult and moved to the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn in the late 1980s. A single woman in her forties, Hoen's life revolved around her career in radio broadcasting at the Chung Wah Commercial Broadcasting Company. When not working, she spent time singing karaoke and Cantonese opera with the Man Chi Opera Society, and attending Sunset Park's traditional Chinese festivals.
  In this interview, Yee "Curie" Hoen describes her life as a single, female Chinese immigrant living alone in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. Leung recounts the process of getting a job as a disk jockey at a Chinese radio station and her promotion to supervisor of the Programming Department. She discusses neighborhood ethnic relations and crime (including being mugged). Hoen tells of her leisure activities; singing karaoke and opera, attending Sunset Park's traditional Chinese festivals, and watching soap operas. Interview conducted by Ka-Kam Chui.
  Brooklyn Chinese American Association.; Hoen, Yee; Mak, Paul; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Festivals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Local transit |z New York (State) |z New York; Opera |z New York (State) |z New York; Radio |z United States |y 20th century; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Huang, Way Ling, 1993 April 16; 1994.007.14
  Access to this recording is restricted by the donor. Please contact library@brooklynhistory.org for further questions.
  Huang, Way Ling; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.)
- Ka, Mak Shui, 1993 November 13; 1994.007.15
  Mak Shui Ka was born in Naahn Sehk Village, in China's Guangdong Province, to a wealthy, prominent family. She grew up with servants and attended the country's most prestigious schools. Her family's fortunes reversed during the opium suppression effort, which drove the family business into the ground, and the Communist "liberation," which repossessed her family's estate and brought persecution to her father. Ka relocated to America and eventually settled with her husband and three children in New York City. In Brooklyn, Ka took on odd jobs and experienced poverty for the first time. She persevered and joined the Seamstresses' Union, the Coalition of Women, and became a community organizer; championing the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn's Chinese community and pursuing anti-discrimination activity. At the time of the 1993 interview, Ka lived happily in Sunset Park with her husband; her three adult children lived nearby.
  In this interview, Mak Shui Ka discusses her life's history in Communist China; upbringing, schools, her family, and persecution, as well as her successes as a conscripted cadet. Mrs. Ka describes her life in America, which brought her first experiences with poverty and grave anti-Chinese discrimination. She describes an extensive anti-Chinese pogrom waged by the Italian members of the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. In response, Ka helped organize a community protest event and delivered a speech that vowed constant vigilance. She details extensively another incident of discrimination in which police stormed an apartment in the Chinatown neighborhood of Manhattan, then beat the family inside; including a pregnant woman. Ka was called as a community first responder; taking photographs and witness testimony, and helped prosecute the police members. In relation to Sunset Park, Ka also references her real estate transactions, the rent prices and taxes, and neighborhood crime. Interview in Cantonese conducted by Ka-Kam Chui.
  Ka, Mak Shui; Koch, Ed, 1924-; Mak, Paul; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); China |x History |x Cultural Revolution, 1966-1976; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic relations; Guangdong Sheng (China); Guangzhou (China); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police brutality |z United States; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Real property |x Valuation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Kang, Harrison, 1993 April 15; 1994.007.16
  Harrison Kang and his family immigrated to America from South Korea in 1980, approximately twelve years prior to this 1993 interview. Kang attended high school and college in New York City; and after a brief stint at a job on Long Island, he returned to Brooklyn to work in his parents' dry cleaning shop. At the time of interview, Harrison Kang was thirty-one years old.
  This brief interview was conducted at the Kang family's dry cleaning shop, located at 5214 Eighth Avenue in Brooklyn. In the interview, Harrison Kang mentions his family's emigration from South Korea to New York City. He describes different aspects of the evolution of the Brooklyn neighborhood of Sunset Park; from relative quietude to a bustling area of immigrants and small business. Kang discusses the neighborhood's change from a mix of Norwegian and Hispanic residents to a primarily Chinese population. By the time of the 1993 interview, Sunset Park was considered Brooklyn's Chinatown. Kang provides an overview of the different ethnic groups endemic to different area streets. Interview conducted by Mary Lui.
  Kang, Harrison; Asian Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Demographic surveys; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Lee, Fai Ling, 1993 November 17; 1994.007.17
  Fai Ling "Alice" Lee was born in Mainland China circa the 1950s, moved to Hong Kong aged three, and immigrated to New York City at fifteen. Her family initially lived in the Bronx before settling in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. She attended Hunter College and worked in the New York City municipal finance department before taking time off to have children and raise a family. During her seven-year maternity leave, Lee nurtured her interest in real estate and began part-time work at a real estate agency. At the time of the interview, Lee worked in bilingual education at P.S. 314 in Sunset Park.
  In this interview, Fai Ling "Alice" Lee discusses the development of the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn; from a sleepy, dilapidated, majority-Norwegian area in the 1970s to a thriving Chinese diaspora in the 1980s and 1990s. She describes the economic and working conditions faced by her father, who worked in a Times Square Chinese restaurant, and her mother, a seamstress in the Chinatown neighborhood of Manhattan. The interview focuses on real estate investing in Sunset Park; home prices, mortgages, rental income, and risks. Lee also mentions her position as a bilingual educator at P.S. 314 in Sunset Park. Interview in Cantonese conducted by Ka-Kam Chui.
  Lee, Fai Ling; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z New York; Norwegians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Real estate business |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Real estate business |z New York (State) |z Queens County; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); Working class |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Lee, Johnny, 1993 September 2; 1994.007.18
  "Johnny Lee" was born circa 1961 in Hong Kong, China, the youngest of five siblings. He immigrated to New York City as a teenager, and finished high school at Seward Park High School in the Chinatown neighborhood of Manhattan. The son of a working-class family, Lee sewed buttons in a Chinatown garment factory during high school, and washed dishes at a Chinatown restaurant as a young man. He attended City College for one year before leaving to pursue stable government work at an Off-Track Betting branch. At the time of the interview, Lee was in his forties and lived with his wife and three children in the three-family home that his parents purchased and converted into a five-family house.
  In this interview, using a pseudonym, "Johnny Lee" recounts his life history. He recollects being raised in Hong Kong by his mother while his father worked in America. He remembers his time at Chinatown's Seward Park High School's bilingual program, classmates who dropped out to join Chinese gangs, after-school work as a button-sewer in garment factories, college work as a dishwasher at a Chinese restaurant, and the decision to leave City College to pursue full-time work at an Off-Track Betting location. Lee discusses the boom in the Chinatown neighborhood of Manhattan’s garment factories, the increase in competition, and resultant deflation in real wages and living standards. He talks about working-class income, real estate prices, his family's decision to purchase a home, and the rejuvenation of the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn and its Eighth Avenue small businesses. Interview in Cantonese conducted by Ka-Kam Chui.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Child labor |z New York (State) |z New York; Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; English as a second language; Factories |z New York (State) |z New York; Gangs |z New York (State) |z Kings Country; High school students |z New York (State) |z New York; Hong Kong (China); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z New York; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); Working class |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Leung, Yee Ming, 1993 September 8; 1994.007.19